So far we've seen how to use for loops to count from one to some larger number,
到目前为止 我们学习了怎么用 for 循环从 1 一直计数到较大的数字
but there's a few more things we can do with for loops.
但我们还可以用 for 循环来做些别的
For example, we don't always have to start with one.
比如 我们不一定要从 1 开始
Say you want to write a function that adds the numbers from 15 to 20,
假设你想写一个函数 从 15 一直累加到 20
so 15 + 16 all the way to 20 and then return the total sum.
即 15 加 16 再一直加到 20 然后返回总和
Our function would be written as
函数要这么写
public int addNumbers and it doesn't take any parameters in,
public int addNumbers 该函数没有输入参数
but returns an integer which is the total sum.
但会返回一个整数 也就是总和
The first thing we would do is initialize our sum
首先我们把变量 sum 初始化为 0
variable to zero and then we start our loop.
然后开始循环
Here we could have our loop,
这里我们可以给循环
have a variable i which is our loop counter start from 15.
一个变量 i 也就是我们的循环计数器 一开始将其设为 15
And our condition can be i &lt;= 20 and then our increment would be i ++.
然后条件可以是 i &lt;= 20 增量就是 i ++
Inside the loop, we would normally add i
在循环里面 通常我们会把 i
to our sum and update the sum with this new value.
和 sum 相加 然后将 sum 更新为相加后的新值
Once the loop finishes,
等到循环结束
we would end up with the total number that is
我们就能得到总和
15 + 16 all the way to 20 and return it as our functions return.
也就是 15 加 16 一直加到 20 的结果 然后作为函数结果返回出来
Let's actually trace this loop and see exactly what's happening.
我们来跟踪这个循环 看看具体会发生什么
We first start with sum being initialized to zero,
先将 sum 初始化为 0
so our value is zero and then we step into the loop initializing i to be 15.
所以这个值为 0 然后进入循环 把 i 初始化为 15
And because i is less than or equal to 20 it's true,
因为 i 小于或等于 20 条件为真
so we step in the loop and then we run this statement here,
所以进入循环 执行这个语句
which is sum = sum + i.
也就是 sum = sum + i
Sum was zero. Sum plus i is 15 so sum
sum 为 0 所以 sum 加 i 为 15
gets updated to the result of this calculation here which is 15.
所以 sum 更新为本计算的结果 也即 15
We reach the end of our loop.
到达循环尾部
We go back up, we increment our counter making it
我们回到这上面来 给计数器增量
16 and then we perform our check operation here,
使其为 16 然后进行这里的判断
is i less than or equal to 20?
i 是否小于或等于 20 呢？
Yes it is. We step back in,
是的 所以我们再进入循环
we add i to the sum again and then update sum,
再次把 i 和 sum 相加 更新 sum 的值
so we add i to the sum which is 15 + 16 then the result gets
把 i 和 sum 相加 也就是 15 加 16
updated into the sum variable which is 31 and so on.
变量 sum 更新为相加的结果 31 以此类推
So we increment i again to be 17,
所以再次给 i 增量 使其为 17
we do our comparison which is true,
进行比较 仍为真
we step inside updating sum and then increment i and then
进入循环 更新 sum 给 i 增量
do our comparison and then update sum increment i,
进行比较 更新 sum 给 i 增量
comparison sum, increment i, comparison.
比较 求和 给 i 增量 比较
So at this point sum is equal to 105.
到这里 sum 等于 105
We reach our end of our loop, we go back up,
我们到了循环尾部 回来
we increment i to make it 21 and then we do our comparison here which is i&gt;= 20.
将 i 增量为 21 进行这里的比较 也就是 i 是否小于或等于 20
Now i is 21 so this comparison is false,
现在 i 为 21 于是比较结果为假
which means we do not step into the loop anymore.
也就意味着我们不会再进入循环
We go here which says return sum,
我们到了这里 要返回 sum
so our function ends returning the value of sum which is 105,
所以函数结束 返回出了 sum 的值 也就是 105
and that is the correct value.
这个计算结果是对的
The idea here is that because we started i with a value
这里的思路就是 因为我们一开始不是将 i 设为 1
not one just 15 and our loop condition went all the way to 20,
而是 15 而循环条件会一直判断到 20
you could see that i changes from 15 all the way till it exits the loop.
所以你可以看到 i 是从 15 一直往上变化的 直到跳出了循环
Another thing you can do with four loops is count downwards rather than up.
用 for 循环还可以做另一件事 那就是递减计算 而非递增
For example, this loop counts up from one all the way to three.
比如 这个循环是从 1 递增算到 3 的
If we run it, we'll get this output one, two, three.
如果我们执行这个循环 就会得到这个输出结果 1、2、3
This is all because of i ++ here which is our loop increment.
这都是这个 i ++ 造成的 因为它是循环增量
It's increasing i by one every time making it go from one,
每次它都会给 i 加 1
to two, to three.
于是 i 就会从 1 变为 2 再变为 3
However, if we wanted our output to become three to one,
然而 如果我们想让输出结果从 3 递减为 1
count down from three to one,
也就是从 3 一直倒数到 1
we can use the notation i --.
我们可以用这个符号 i --
Just like i ++ is adding one to i and updating it that way,
就像 i ++ 是给 i 加 1 然后更新 i
i -- is subtracting one from i and updating it that way as well.
i -- 是给 i 减 1 然后更新 i
It's called the decrement,
这叫做减量
because i is decreasing every time.
因为 i 每次都会减少
And it's exactly the same as saying i = i -1.
这与写 i = i -1 完全相同
It's just the short hand version of it.
不过是把公式简写了而已
However once we use i --, we're counting down.
不过我们用 i -- 的话 计数器就会倒数
So we want our loop to start from the larger number this time which would be three.
所以这次我们希望循环能从一个大点的数字开始计数 也就是 3
So i starts from three and it counts downwards.
因此 i 会从 3 开始倒数
But our loop condition also needs to change.
不过循环条件也得改一下
Can you try to figure out what this loop condition should be?
你能想出这个循环条件该改成什么样吗？